hi moroc
excellent i'm looking forward to the
conversation so nice to see you again
yeah me too yeah and you and it's
gosh when was it that i was actually
over in your
lovely island that must have been about
a year ago now i think
the the thing is it isn't actually that
long ago but with what has happened
since
it feels like it was in a different
light on a different planet but yeah
rather it does indeed and yeah about a
year a little bit
little bit yeah i think it was just over
a year ago and the thing is that
it's stuck with me so much you know some
places are really sticky
other places you kind of forget the
details and the sort of a distant memory
there's something about where we were
and i'm i mean particularly
some milan and and you know the
conversations that we had there walking
around
you know through that ancient olive
grove just there's a
something about you know where you are
is just absolutely magical
and i feel it as i walk around here
every day this sort of it always enters
into my mind at some point in the day
yeah i think we need to be really
grateful
for living in places that actually have
that capacity to
to sort of pattern us in a healing way
that are just so ancient and
where people have put such care
like in crystal waters for example i
think it's
it becomes a feedback loop i've lived
this at finton where
by so many people with real attention to
detail and place
and and respect of place trying to
um be good custodians of the land and
and and bring it to life eventually as
the place comes to life
i i feel it it actually gives back to us
in in
so many ways and um i
i felt that at finton i feel it here in
in the mountains where people have
over millennia built these terraces and
and
taking care of olives that are sometimes
yeah
nine hundred a thousand years old um
very special
and it's remarkable isn't it you feel
that care in that landscape you feel the
you know the love that must have been
imbued in in
creating those amazing places and
everything's crafted and handcrafted and
i'm you know and i'm thinking
you know coming back here into crystal
waters i was chatting to someone who
has recently moved here and
was just mentioning about how every day
they go for a walk and they just sit
beside either one of the lakes or the
river or
walk up to the top of the hill where
they've got sort of a 360 view around
the
national parks and just say how
absolutely healing the place is and you
know sometimes
you need to have that reflected back at
you i've been here for 20 years now and
i mean i feel that on a daily basis but
sometimes
you do take it for granted when you're
just within it and i'm
maybe you know i really like i really
like being able to have that
that sort of sense of connection and
sense of healing and sense of
specialness um uh reminded
given a reminder but i mean there's
something
particular about the wildlife here that
just
brings me to brings me alive every day
we're surrounded by kangaroos and
wallabies
and you know every day i i wake up and
there's like there's a
there's a family that lives here with us
in this place i mean we don't keep them
they just come past we
and there's kangaroo trails everywhere
and anyway so this
little family and you get to know each
um you know each successive family that
this mother
brings into the into the into the place
and
and it's beautiful it's so nice to watch
a you know out the window or even just
sitting out in the garden with them
a little baby joey come out of the pouch
for the first time and sort of try and
find its legs and just wobbling all over
the place and
and the sound of the birds and and
there's that deep sense of
joy in being having a deep relationship
with like the more than human
and and starting to hear the different
sounds and the signals and the
the changes that happen and and start to
feel that signaling something else and
it's only when
we sort of slow down enough and spend
enough time in place that i think we
start
to reconnect with that and i think maybe
there's something about that
maybe that's something that's a
re-indigenizing process
i don't know i i don't know necessarily
how to describe that but i feel
i feel an essence of that when i have
these experiences
well i i wanted to ask you about that
because in many ways you've lived
um how long have you been now at crystal
waters over 20 years over 20 years now
so so you've lived over the last 20
years something that
i've held as my high vision of what i
wanted to do at some point in my life
um the the whole process of
really arriving on a piece of land and
saying um
this is where i take my stand this is
this is where i'm going to grow roots
and and try to help this place thrive
and and
and build a place where my family and my
community can thrive
and um how how has that been for you
because
you're are you originally from brisbane
or you lived in brisbane before you
moved i'm originally from melbourne the
outskirts of melbourne i grew up in the
suburbs
of melbourne um but the suburbs were not
it wasn't like a jam-packed suburb it
was quite
a sort of a hilly natural landscape i
grew up on a quarter acre block which is
quite standard for the outskirts of
melbourne
although it was a little bit different
because my mum and dad built our house
there
and so i had this sense of what it meant
to live in an owner-built house and
a house that had passive solar design
and
and being really truly engaged in in
managing a building to be efficient and
and knowing where the where those rocks
came from or
how that bit of balcony was put together
and so i guess that sense and
my mum was we grew a little bit of food
in the backyard but it wasn't a big
thing although they talked about it
what my parents were really focused on
and it was a big thing in that you know
sort of the 70s was um bringing back the
native
uh plants to attract wildlife and create
spaces for birds so there was always
that sense
of this is a space for nature and we're
trying to
protect that and to regenerate nature i
kind of grew up within that sort of
space so
i'd often heard about crystal waters i
went through landscape architecture
environmental planning design urban
design kind of school
in melbourne and i'd always watched this
place that had started to be talked
about
um in southeast queensland and
uh so i hadn't been there until after i
went to schumacher college and i was um
also
i worked with helena norberg hodge in
ladakh and experiencing
when was that back in 92
yeah so yeah so i'd
i'd i learned i was
learning about what it meant to live a
sustainable life i could
say what it was i could write an essay
about it i could
you know talk about it and then i went
to ladakh
and there was this community where that
was totally embedded in the landscape
that everything came from the earth and
went back to the earth and it was this
there was a great sense of joy and
connectedness
you know and there was an enormous sense
of wealth even though there was no money
being exchanged and we
and so i came back thinking how do we
leave such a rich
place-connected community-connected
joyful regenerative life back here in
australia
and it's when i re-embraced permaculture
again because i'd known about it for
ages my parents had always talked about
it
as something that was kind of like if if
you have any sense about you
this is what you should be looking at
you know that was kind of always put in
that little pigeon hole like
anyone who's who has good common sense
looks at permaculture and
and there was always the books on the
shelf you know they always got talked
about
and um and so i thought okay now's the
time to take that permaculture course
and and also to go and visit crystal
waters and so i did this
two things together and i came here and
one sorry what was that who was the
teacher on that course was it max or
yeah and francis um michaels who started
up the
uh the green harvest the organic
seeds placed and also a woman called
um her name is just
jill jordan who started up the let
system
uh in australia and also stand up the
local community cooperative banks and
the whole cooperative movement in
melania
and it was that that really inspired me
anyway i fell in love with
christa waters and i also fell in love
with this boat called evan
and and um and that was that
basically uh we we both weren't living
at crystal waters at the time he was
living in brisbane
so i basically moved up to brisbane
and we started the city farm together we
our goal was actually to create an eco
village in the middle of brisbane
and it was just too hard with all the
planning laws and it was
so we thought okay what's the
low-hanging fruit and our the group that
we were working we thought okay well
let's just start the food bit
the gardens and and then from that
community
was the the community that formed around
that was extraordinary we created
you know organic farmers markets and
food box systems and
yoga groups and kids groups and people
started to move into the neighborhood
around the city farm and so
by default we were creating this urban
eco village
even though it wasn't you know an
intentional village that was created
and well i know five years into that um
we got invited to come up to crystal
waters to see if we wanted to take on
running the permaculture courses here
um because max was pulling back and we
said sure
ecological solutions or something at the
time
yeah yeah yeah so he was sort of pulling
back i think because he was
focusing more on the work with jen at
that time which was just starting out
and uh yeah so we so we stepped in and
did that and just you know those moments
where
everything just happens at the right
time
so evan's mum had just um
decided to buy a house here at crystal
waters and so she we said okay we'll
we'll stay in the cabin and you can rent
out that because she wasn't ready to
move there
so we had a house to live in we had work
with the permaculture courses
and um my dad had just retired at the
same time and he and he
he was looking for ethical investments
and we said well there's a block of land
that we'd really love to buy
so he he basically put up the money for
us
at the half of it that we needed to to
actually get our own place here and then
we started
building over time so yes it was
everything just kind of
was right for us to move here and then
we've never looked back
absolutely absolutely love living here
raised our family here
built a house the only little bit of
debt that we went into
was with my dad just to get the land and
everything since then
we've done without any debt so we've
built our house
module by module we started off i'm in
the office
at the moment which started out as a
shed and then it became our house
and uh and now it's my office and so we
have these
what i call buildable affordable modules
that uh
enable us and so a lot of people have
actually come and had a look at this and
thought well that's a really good way to
to get started you start with one little
core bit and then you just keep adding
and adding it as you can
um and it's it's been really great and
just to watch my kids growing up
it's it's one of the things that that i
was reflecting on a lot when i was
living in finton
um and working with jen in different
ways how
so many of the model eco villages have
been
built at a time where um planning
regulations were different
and um where it was somewhat
easier to like to still encounter a sort
of sandbox where you could
just go ahead and do it and then build a
relationship with the local planning
office and eventually get
illegal buildings recertified and and so
on and so forth
and um it there seems to be really a
need
if we want more people to engage more in
this
reinhabitation process and careful
stewarding of land
to to create new planning regulations
that say
as long as you have a regenerative
impact on the land
and you hit these requirements
we will make it easy for you to to get
past the official planning goals because
in many ways they're there to protect
the land from being destroyed um
in in some cases not that people with
lots of money then somehow always
navigate past those laws
but um but i noticed this here in in
majorca for example in the tremontana
where we were
at sevilla's place this wonderful place
on roland if you try to do anything in
sunru land
and that would basically use this place
for example as a teaching center
[Music]
just slightly building infrastructure so
you could actually
house people even if you did it in the
most respectful way
it would be almost impossible to get
planning permission for anything because
it's a unesco world heritage site
and so um sometimes the
the laws that protect the land from
infringing of development
also impede sort of innovative eco
regenerative development um and it's
yeah that's right we lived as
it's a similar type of thing too with um
you know people
uh protecting farmland landscapes or
protecting
uh you know national parks you know
saying okay this is a national park
and lock it up and then the indigenous
people can't live there and create
villages there
or you know but it the intent is to
protect it but it's actually
destroying it because it is a
people-managed landscape in and of
itself or
the farm landscapes that as it's changed
from being a
working farm into sort of more just as a
a nice looking hillside for
the rich people to live up on the hills
there's you know it's changed already
those things so
the farmland needs people taking people
out of the farmland
you know turns it in well here in
australia it just turns it into these
sort of
weed infested fields that are have lost
their fertility they actually need
the ongoing you know management and and
more people in and on those landscapes
so i'm watching
as crystal waters land is actually able
to be regenerated and i'm
looking at places like uh wales where
they do the
the one planet development where the
government's actually saying
okay if if you're going to do
regenerative type of development
we can talk about how you can get a
piece of land and build a community
off-grid and do it differently than say
what you would down near the town
and so we do need these this flexible
way of doing it and i'm
only seeing a couple of councils that
are being a little bit more
flexible like this now it goes in in
waves
i sort of feel like crystal waters has
has a relationship with the council that
means that it is able to be a little bit
more experimental i mean i still all my
buildings are still
um absolutely to the book there's
there's nothing that's not approved
about what i do with them
except we've pushed the boundary with
things like the toilet system
or the wastewater system and so we've
done
education around that with the public
plumbing department and with
you know the the local councillors to
actually shift
the boundary and then we're seeing that
ripple out so it's they're places of
innovation and
and it's when that's able to happen
that's great but i know that there's a
lot of limitations in a lot of places
that's a classic like those examples
like for example the straw bale building
at um fintorn uh the large one
was really the first in scotland and
um so the planning department really had
to
use it as a case to learn about straw
bale building and whether
and how they might make sense scotland
or similarly in germany the
um at um it's even linden equal village
when they started building in multi
stories with it like a timber
timber frame and then straw bale infill
um
they basically wrote the planning rules
on how to
build structurally sound multi-storey
strawberry buildings
um but but what we expect
like what we're experiencing here on
majorca at the moment i'm
starting to help miguel ramis with this
project of
trying to get serious about landscape
regeneration and experimenting with the
kind of
bioproductivity that we can generate in
a climate
change influenced future so so really
looking into
the different areas on majorca that
represent the four growing zones of the
mediterranean
and then um seeing what we can do to to
build soil to bring back the rain to
increase um like build microclimates
that
allow for more diverse productivity but
even if you try to do stuff like that
um you run into laws
that will stop you or at least delay you
by
sometimes a year and a half two years
three years so for example i was a bit
disappointed when i when i realized that
just something as simple as digging
a natural water reservoir in the center
or in
in a pro appropriate place on your land
where there's a gully
to to collect water runoff and have a
have another safety in in case of
drought
and and bring back the whole micro
climate that comes with having a body of
water and all the animals that that can
live in it and so on
and it's impossible like it would be
changing the landscape
and for that you then have to make
amazing like what tamera did
in their land like they have a similar
climate and we have here
um very dry area among
a few almond and oak trees and so on
and just by building that really large
lake they've
completely changed the the whole
microclimate
but to do the same here that we've we've
got 17
lakes that are within our landscape and
australia too
it's a very dry landscape and i remember
this being really quite stuck when i
first came here
and seeing the impact of having those 17
lakes put in here is absolutely
remarkable but not only that
there's something um with this new
system um that's
going now which is called um
leaky weirs which is uh it's actually a
united nations
recognized system now for rehydrating
the landscape so it doesn't necessarily
have to be a water body but it's
it's slowing down the water and kind of
filling up gullies to
to back it up and they're transforming
um quite degraded
farmlands using this system and i've
been going up
into the valleys um all around crystal
waters and noticing actually that's
what's been happening naturally
and that's where we're starting to get
that natural regeneration of
of some rainforest species and and the
whole landscape
has changed there it's absolutely
remarkable so i'm going to sort of take
my camera and my video up there and
start to document
the impact that this is having because
it's it's replenishing springs
it's bringing back shade it's actually
helping to restore so when i walk
through there
now it feels like i'm walking on a
sponge when you go
out a bit further it feels like you're
just walking back on hard land
there's something that's happening there
that's just bringing life back into the
soil
and so when i start to think about a lot
of these limitations and the reasons
behind these limitations it really does
make us think that we need to take that
whole bi-regional perspective
and start to be talking at that meta
level you know like the
the um the road maps with the common
earth road maps
so these bi-regional areas that are
actually exploring different ways of
doing things and looking at it as being
this
it's a global movement with bioregional
examples and we need to
link in with with that to be able to to
get some
local action and local loosening of laws
or redesigning laws to be
in support of regeneration instead of
purely heritage like how can you support
heritage and the future
at the same time because you know the
way things are now i mean i remember
walking through those landscapes as
beautiful as they were
there was a sense of that the soil was
completely depleted
you know if if you to support yourself
from those terraces and from those
landscapes a completely different way of
managing them would be needed
and it's possible to have both and
wouldn't that be amazing to actually
bring those terraces back to life again
with
you know with an amazing polyculture and
and a sense of rehydration of those by
thinking about you know the whole entire
catchments
it's it's totally possible but it does
require a shift
in thinking and a bi-regional approach
yeah and
the thing is on the one hand it's kind
of
you really have to work globally on this
in the sense that
the global networking around this vision
and
um the building of alliances between
kind of alliances of the willing of
people who are already
understanding the importance of working
by originally and that
that's the wonderful thing that there
are now lots of different organizations
that
have um somehow arrived at the
bioregional scale
from different angles so i find it for
example really fascinating that the the
planetary health alliance which
which to some extent is still somewhat
stuffy
health policy researchers and academics
um
looking at population health um
but the very fact that they've put at
the center that
um planetary health and ecosystems
health is fundamental for human and
population health
and that um if we want to decrease
national spending on health the best way
to do so is to actually help like like
improve the local ecosystem
and that's that plays very strongly in
our direction and and
and also the fact that they they
recognize that
bioregional health maintaining the
health of watersheds is
is a scale that is is a sensible
approach
um but for me
the issue is sometimes that on the one
hand you need to bring in that global
alliance
um in order to then have the critical
master say look this is not
a local group of visionaries saying we
need to do this this
there are visionaries of this type in
every continent of the
planet and very serious well
uh like like people with good track
records of doing real projects
and and they're all working on this um
that then helps to maybe influence
planning departments but what the minute
you actually go into your
place it opens up in the other direction
as a fractal
of complexities that um
like just working with the whole
structure of land ownership and how
how to build the alliances and and
constantly how to get past regulations
both at national
um local and international level because
how do you like when you try to
jump start diverse
sort of value-added agricultural
economies in a region that come along
with
a re-inhabitation of the land and more
more ice-to-acre
ratio and more work on on regenerating
landscape and making it more productive
you can bring in lots of innovation in
in
new buyer materials bio
biopharmaceuticals
all sorts of areas um but
if those small businesses have to
compete with rules that were supposedly
protecting workers or protecting
health but they basically the classic
example here in europe is always
the little 300 year old cheese maker
somewhere in france
that has to close down because they
can't put tiles on the ceiling
of the kitchen whether that cheese has
been made for generations
because some law says now for hygiene
reasons you have to have tiles
on ceilings and floors yeah it's it's
those kind of things that we also need
to
really look at um like where i was going
earlier is that
miguel ramirez and i have realized that
to create these four pilot projects
around mallorca doing this work you
actually have to talk to the government
and declare them some somehow
zones of innovation and and and somehow
get a new kind of
um precedence put through the legal
system that says
there are certain areas where people are
trying to do innovative things around
um eco settlements regeneration of the
land um
rehydrating the land reforestation soil
building
and so on and so forth and we can't slow
them down with
with all that red tape we we can just
let them do and then we come after the
fact and we study what they've done and
certify it
but i think that's absolutely critical
as having those
those spaces and places where people can
experiment and
that you can set it up and they can
see what's happening and it's in it's an
example that they can look to that
it may work it may not work it may work
in different ways than you
imagine but there's a place that you can
start to demonstrate that
and and i just um actually just in uh
kenya
just yesterday i've been talking with a
group there recently we've just got to
the point now where the
um the agriculture minister has given a
piece of land
uh and support to actually set up a
demonstration
and then that will be the place where
extension workers can come in and start
to learn and then be able to rip all
that out
it just needs a place and from that
place
to be a and that that maybe it's a bit
relaxed it's something special that
you work with them to get excited about
that the same thing happened with the
city farm in brisbane
there were no rules for city farms to
happen there were there was no
urban agriculture to happen in the city
there
there was no there were no rules for
growing and harvesting food
by community on community land uh
we had to kind of break the rules a bit
and work
closely in conjunction with them and
they i remember actually in the very
first
uh meetings with the mayor saying okay
well we'll come back and we'll look at
this in a year we'll give you a year to
kind of
we'll see how you go in that time and
they they actually didn't come back
in a year i noticed in that next year we
were there
on their platform for re-election
because they realized what a such a good
project was and what
great traction it had created in
generating
interest around sustainable living in
the city and i can imagine as soon as
these projects do start to happen that
all these other things will start to
emerge out of it and the
the uh sort of the new ideas and the
excitement and the emergence of
possibilities will just start to come
out of those it's kind of like this
there's this mycelium network that's
going on all over the place
and it starts to connect wherever we put
compost on it starts to
really you know get very busy underneath
and then all of a sudden these places
that pop up which is the flowering the
fruiting body of this mycelium network
and then
if we shine a light on that enough and
it starts to
mature and and then the spores kind of
start to go out it's just
it's like that we need these little
mushroom these mushrooms to come up
and uh and that's what those examples
are that people can see and and
it does mean pushing boundaries it does
mean
people relaxing regulations it does mean
making exceptions and i don't think it's
until we get that that we can start to
kind of take a quantum leap out of where
we are now
but it does take that big picture
thinking and to excite other people
about being part of that big picture
thinking
it's interesting because this reminds me
of a conversation i had with joel
glansberg and
and you know how i love all that that
the whole
kind of regenesis tribe and their deep
work
in regenerative developments and
sometimes i kind of bump into a certain
things that
that they have a little bit of sort of
no nose um
where i kind of say well maybe it's a
yes and rather than a no no
um kind of thing that's the only bit
where i sometimes
don't resonate with with their approach
the
kind of clear delineation of well that's
not working regeneratively
and in in in one conversation with joe
he was explaining his wonderful work
world with this
um this drylands um
permaculture research institute and and
and building up
a demonstration site in in a really
tricky climate kind of
high altitude desert in near thousand
new mexico
and um how he when they
had put in all this amazing work to
basically create this oasis in the
middle of a
desertifying region um and he
created a little video to sort of
zooming in
on on google maps onto this this little
oasis and you could see the desert and
then
this green spot would appear and and
then he
said that when he'd finish that video
and about this place
he initially was very chuffed and then
in the middle of the night woke up
and and realized that he kind of
been climbing up the wrong ladder or the
rather that was leaning against the
wrong wall kind of thing or
like that that he'd actually it wasn't a
success but somehow it was a failure
because it was only that small piece of
land
and the area around it had stayed the
same and and so he was saying
what process could i have worked on that
would have done what what you just sort
of described and that's where i find the
two come together
that we need to create these
demonstration spots but
but what happens with the energy that
goes into demonstration sites because it
is so difficult very often
people disappear into their local
project what happened with so many eco
villages where
without any negative intention the
the kind of intentional community
settlers just focused on getting their
infrastructure up
and before they knew it they were 20
years into the story and had kind of
forgotten the the relationship with the
wider
region because they were so busy on
their project
and and i think what we've learned from
i totally agree
from that first wave is that we do need
to do both we need to
it's it's hard work and it takes most of
the effort initially
to do the work on the ground locally but
but the more you
from the beginning work with others in
your region that are also doing
something similar and the more you
coordinate actions in order to do these
things like changing planning laws
building inroads to to local government
and even building inroads to to um there
are some
regional businesses that are happy to
fund
positive projects in their region and
and we need to like a bit sort of like
what judy wicks did with with bali i
think it's just changed name
it's common something yeah did you
remember the
real name of bali i know it is barley i
didn't know the changed name
yeah um the business aligned for local
local living economies
um they just changed commons future or
something
other i can't remember anyway but but it
is um
for me i'm talking so much about it
because i find that tension quite strong
at the moment
how to how to refocus my attention more
to the local because i feel like if
you've done 20 years of doing wonderful
work building courses
but i've also seen you in in really
effective ways
reach beyond this demonstration
site and an institute and so i'd love to
hear a little bit more like
share with because you do all these
wonderful interviews with people on your
on your
um youtube channel and now you started a
podcast
and um and i i would
love to hear more about your story
because you you set up the the
permaculture
education institute and and then
our permaculture live youtube channel
and and you're doing some work in
in africa and then then i've found
something called ethos foundation
um which i don't know anything about
tell me a bit more about
about the different projects yeah okay
all right
so i mean right from the very start i
i realized that it it's just exactly
what you said it's not enough just to do
this project it's always about how
there's that relationship elsewhere like
even for example with that
just going back to that city farm
project that as we were doing that work
rather than getting drawn in and just
focusing on that what we would do every
time we'd have these um
monthly gatherings and we'd get people
to bring food down to share and what we
would do we would raise money
um for a project somewhere else in the
world so maybe it would have been um
in africa or bhutan or indigenous
community and there would be
and we'd start to realize that there's
projects all around the world
in every community that are doing
similar things to us and that by doing
what we're doing
it's lifting this whole movement and so
i guess that sense
always of telling the story so i started
out telling the story locally i would go
and
share with communities and i'd go on
local radio
and and just keep on sharing that story
out and then going and visiting places
and bringing those stories back
and so always that sharing sharing
stories sharing
trying to sort of build a narrative
around this um
i got invited by the brisbane city
council which is
uh it's kind of an interesting council
that it is really a regional council
it's one of the biggest
councils in the world i think uh and so
they invited me to come in and write a
sustainable food policy for their
metropolitan planning
process to look at how to integrate you
know city farms and community gardens
and community food systems and
street trees and all different sorts of
things into their planning thinking
so uh when was that oh gosh um
2005 i know maybe before then i'm
sorry i'm a little bit vague on that but
so
so the idea was that you know that what
we're learning and then also people
would be constantly
calling me up and saying i'd like to get
a community gun starting can you come
and help us and i was getting so many
calls
that i started up with a group of
friends something called the australian
city farms and community gardens network
and then we started gathering people
around so that we'd build this
sort of reference group and a mutual
learning group
and so that's still going now so always
trying to take the learning from
locally and and building that out making
it visible making it available
and then from so now based here at
crystal waters
there's a few different things that you
mentioned i
used to mostly do face-to-face teaching
and it was
people would come here to crystal waters
and they would be doing a permaculture
course
and they'd be coming from all around the
world because crystal waters is a united
nations world habitat award-winning eco
village and so
it's a place that people came to have a
look so we would typically have half the
people from
australia around australia and half the
people from around the world i guess
similar to in finton those people from
all over coming
and so they would come here and then
they would say oh this is
this is amazing could you come to our
community and
and teach a course like this and help us
to run and get a program set up so then
we would go
to that community so evan and i were
based pre kids were basically traveling
around the world
teaching permaculture courses visiting
communities and
just and then learning along the way and
bringing that back in so this is
constant exchange
and then we started the digital age
started to enter and that's
when i i kind of didn't really get into
it to start with and eventually
there was a woman called rhonda hetzel
this is this is her book down to earth
she's now 70 something and um
she took me under i interviewed her at
the real food festival one day
and she said to me i've got this blog
you know this is her book which is a
bestseller
but she she said i've got this blog and
it's like over 20 million people have
read my blog
all about simple living she said you
really ought to have a blog
what's a blog i have no idea what a blog
was so she took
his seven-year-old woman took me under
her wing and said look you need to get
online
and so so i did and it's been the best
thing ever because i
i really just always thought it was so
important to be face to face and to
really have
you know the group and be in situ and
i mean i still do that as much as i can
even though covert doesn't make that
possible but now
i've also yeah so i've created the
youtube channel and the blog and
and that's all the our permaculture life
type of things it's really looking at
what does what does a one planet life
look like
when did you start the block just
roughly like
um about 2015 2016.
yeah okay yeah i kind of i didn't do any
social media until my book came out
so i kind of um was complete neo fight
in
any of this facebook i really didn't
want to waste my time in
and and so on um but it's yeah
it's mushrooming um i i find it yeah
yeah
it's important work but it's also uh
it's like to
how again it's a question of balance how
to keep putting this out
and keeping the local practice going
well what i'm finding interesting now is
um so you asked about the ethos
foundation so i have the
so i have um there's our permaculture
life which is the community education
i run master classes so the master
classes i run every month and they they
have about
2 000 people who sign up to those and
then there's videos that go out i've
just started a podcast and just recently
interviewed um frichoff capra and
um just about to interview the um the
founder of one million women and
and that's called sense making and
changing world so that's all the things
that i just
um stories that i'm gathering and
sharing and putting out into the world
then there's a permaculture education
institute which is where i'm
my goal with that is to try and teach as
many new permaculture teachers
as possible so that it's not just you
know a hobby but it's actually a way of
life and there's people
who are rippling out into the world
going out and and
actually being of service in communities
everywhere and this being their their
way of life
um so that's online
and what i found what my goal with that
was that every time someone signed up on
that course i would donate a course to
somewhere else
in some part of the world where they
couldn't afford it
and then i got to the point realizing
actually well
they probably don't have the internet to
access this so then i started creating
the ethos foundation and supporting
local courses in places like
like africa um india and
many parts of the world where you know
the different kind of economic
level so mostly i'm focusing in east
africa at the moment so every week
i'm talking with with groups over there
mentoring local teachers who are then
teaching
other teachers and the main pro main
thing that's happening at the moment is
that they're
setting up perma youth groups and these
are even in refugee camps so i'm
mentoring teachers in those camps who
have
groups of kids who are transforming the
landscapes and taking
permaculture back to their their little
huts
and making food gardens around those and
and i was just talking to one woman
sakina today and i was i was asking her
about
she lives in kokuma refugee camp now
kakuma refugee camp is in the north west
dry part of kenya and um
and she's from from from the democratic
republic of congo
and she's been there 11 years and i was
asking her so so really you know what is
the future for you and
you know lots of the people who are
living there there's 200 000 people
living there
and she said look you know there's so
few people who ever get out of here and
go to somewhere like canada or australia
or america
but mostly we're just here this is it
we we have no concept of ever being able
to go back to our country because the
war continues
so we just have to kind of take it that
this is where we are
and so now there's this big wave of
things like permaculture starting to
emerge there to go okay well
how do we make this place a livable
place how do we grow food rather than
just being dependent
on aid and particularly at this point in
time when um
at covert the aid was chopped in half in
terms of their food
there's massive amounts of hunger
happening and so
the the desperate need for people to be
added to
have this knowledge about how to grow um
you know polycultural kitchen gardens
whereas a lot of the
knowledge that they had about growing
was about just
rice and corn rice and corn with sort of
chemical agriculture
type system so there's this real
flourishing of that and so that's what
the ethos foundation is about trying to
support new teachers and also provide
resources for permaculture education
this is wonderful describe to me a
little bit
like a kind of online mentoring call
with one of those local groups
what would you kind of advise them on or
do you do you kind of give them ideas of
what they can do with the kids in terms
of
um little exercises or do you send them
pdfs of
um drawings of a compost toilet or how
do you how do you support them
all of that so but i
really avoid being prescriptive and
saying
okay this is what you need to teach them
go ahead and teach that
so we've had lots of conversations about
you know what is the situation like
they've sent me photographs they've
brought me through with the video camera
um i really asked them what are their
you know what's their situation then we
come together
out and find out what are those what are
the key starting points and so a lot of
it is about
um accessing land and tools and seeds
and
composting systems so i look at what
they've got there and basic things like
composting and mulching and um holly
cultures
um toilet systems all of those sorts of
things um and then the other day i
so i sit sometimes it's with with me and
one of the teachers and
today it was just through whatsapp video
sometimes it's through zoom whichever
way is working at the time
um but every week i also get to talk
with a lot of the young kids and so they
all kind of gather around
the zoom window and there's all of them
in the one window and then there's me in
the other window and
and we have a chat and and so i'm asking
them questions kind of
you know i sometimes i show them a
picture about like a living system of
soil and ask them what they see and we
we kind of explore it and
they talk about their soil and how we
can actually reach a more living soil
system
other times i say what's happening in
your garden today what what are you
struggling with and then now
we kind of uh you know they were saying
they had some problem
and it ended up being not what they
thought so we kind of
we unpacked all that for them um
it it's really whatever it is just but
just last week they
um one of their members died and so
um it was a malaria and it just happened
really quickly so
you know the other thing as well as
sending money for um
you know doing permaculture stuff it's
all it ends up being also people care
because
you know that family then needs support
for the funeral and all those things so
we've got a global premier youth group
who meet with this group each week so
every sunday afternoon
the refugee camp kids are meeting with
kids from um
from england from germany from thailand
australia new zealand
and zanzibar and they all get together
and then when this
young boy died um they raised some money
together and they're
and they're sending that to it just got
delivered to him the other day their
family
and so his sister is now going to join
the group and be part of this which is
so fantastic
um and we've just managed to get a
little bit of money to send them um
so they can get a camera and a
microphone
and we're talking about how much it
costs and all that stuff and he says
i could probably get a little bit
cheaper one so then i could leave a bit
left to get a guitar
and i said oh you want a guitar and he
said yeah because they're all musicians
and we'd love to actually write songs
about
permaculture and this way of doing
things so then we can start to share the
story
more rapidly and further if it's a song
it's going to go
it's going to get shared around so i
said look
don't worry about it i'll let all of
that money for the camera go to the
camera and i'll donate some money for
you to get a guitar i think that's a
brilliant idea so
i'm just trying to respond to whatever
it is that they as a group come up with
and you know it's not a lot of money but
it's a little bit that responds directly
and i don't ask them to report on it i
don't ask them to give me
full documentation of that it's it's
this relationship that's being formed
there
and just as a way to help them
to to i guess meet basic needs
in where they are and i've just got the
little slideshow of all the wonderful
happy faces in projects that you're
working with in africa and that's it's
just really lovely like
um ethosfoundation.org dot a u
i d d can people support this by just
yes please because on on there on that
ethosfoundation.org
there's a donate button and so what and
every money that is donated from that
um comes to me um in an account and
every single dollar i send over there
any administration costs i cover
personally because i'm just trying to
get as much out there so at the moment
um i'm supporting a women's group in in
kakamega to buy
a farmland so they can set up their own
demonstration permaculture farm and
create food sovereignty
micro enterprise there so i've i've put
the first deposit on and
i'm i'm winging it to get the next five
to five payments for them
um i've got three or four perma youth
clubs in the refugee camps that
we're supporting and that when i spoke
to sakida today from kakuma she said
um i'm working with the kids but you
know what i really want to work with the
mamas as well because
then then if i teach the mummers then
i'll have more teachers who can go out
into all the different communities and
work with all the
children so i said great go ahead and um
so now i'm just going to try and raise
the money to support them so again it's
that same thing and that's never very
much
and what i'd like to do actually is to
pay sakina for sakina to be like the
team
leader and to go out and actually run
these programs and to coordinate it and
someone approached me from another part
of that refugee camp
with an extraordinarily high cost and i
asked his can
could you just check out what this
project is and so she went across to the
other side the
camp checked it all out and came back
and said look they're really authentic
please support them and so so we're just
going to start building relationships
with them and so yeah
i've got just these beautiful
connections forming with you know
women's groups
um perma youth groups but the thing that
really excites me is that this
the perma youth global network that's
starting to form
around this and it's it's generative
it's not me coming up with the
curriculum and saying okay i'm going to
teach youth how to do permaculture
it's just emerging and it's so amazing
and so beautiful
tell me a little bit more about this
because i mean and like
mandy and um maddie
all have talked about how do we engage
youth in permaculture for
num number of years and i know you're in
touch with them and
is this all a coordinated um youth and
permaculture
activity because i think they got some
european funding there was even the
meeting in italy at some point
and um because when i when i listened to
you i kind of think
how do you cope with the admin and the
organization are you working
as a network and and people pick up
all this work are you doing all your own
admin
um for all these different approaches
yourself
yeah um
but i having said that um i just
i actually just for the first time i
think we talked about this last time and
i've actually just employed an assistant
to help me to do some of the work not so
much on the perma youth and the ethos
foundation because that's all what i
call my
community service work you know my
permaculture service work but more with
the business side so then i can dedicate
more to this work
but also i have to say that um the perma
youth itself
so um my daughter 14 year old daughter
maya
she she's she runs she puts together the
whole newsletter
she runs the session she sends out all
the invitations she does all the
so she's homeschooling and so that's one
of her home school projects is to run
the perma youth
so i'm i was said i was doing that to
start with but now i've been able to
step back and she's just
dived straight in there to do that um i
talk with mandy quite regularly i also
keep in touch with the children in
permaculture but what we realized when i
was
um over there with mandy was that um
there's the children in permaculture and
i met up with them when i was in wales
um and
yeah in wales and um they're kind of
like the primary school kids
and the the youth in permaculture are
kind of more
the older there's this bit in between
sort of from 10 to 16
this big group of kids who uh a lot of
those are the ones who were out on the
streets with the climate marches
um you know this the student strikes and
there was this sense that actually
that they'd go on the strikes and then
they'd come back to school
or wherever come back home and life
would be the same it's like well what
now
and so really this was a in a response
to that too that
okay this this is everyday activism this
is
kind of we're calling it practicism you
know it's practical activism of
something you can do in your own home in
your own community
so it's kind of fascinating they're
doing music together they're doing art
together they're doing
designs together writing together
they've they're putting together a
little book
together um as well as um talking
and like every day they i mean
what i'm concerned a little bit with all
of us now and
with this pandemic world that we seem to
be in
is that we all end up spending more time
online so when
on the one hand it's wonderful i mean
and even if it is online it's so worth
it
in terms of the learning that you can
have as a privileged
english or german or belgian teenager to
to engage with a
like-minded similar spirit earth care in
intuiting um person in africa or asia or
anywhere in the world i mean it's
priceless it definitely needs to happen
but how how do you how do you make sure
that it doesn't become a kind of virtual
space only
and that that goes back into
them actually engaging with analog
people in their local
community in in 3d space
yeah good question and and that's
something that i've thought
a lot about in particular because the
course that i run the permaculture
design course and permaculture teacher
course is also
an online one and that's really about
how do we
how do we ground that as well so for the
perma youth
in particular um we have little local
hubs
and so for example the group here when
they can they have
local camps um you know the group that's
working in the refugee camp they have
their community garden that they
that they work on and then they take
videos of that and then they share that
with someone else and this group
um there's a boy who who joins him from
sweden and he and his mates get together
and do some gardens there
um and then they send it in and there's
another girl from another part
she works with her local friends doing
um
wild harvesting and so then they share
that in so each group
has their own particular focus and they
do their own particular
local work and then together when they
come
it's this sense of being part of
something much larger than themselves
that before
gardening seemed a little bit maybe not
quite an activism
thing not something that was going to
make any difference in the world but
actually they're realizing that
it is helping people to like
particularly because they
now have this relationship with the
refugees and they're seeing
growing a garden saving your seeds
learning how to compost and mulch
is the difference between life and death
the gardening
and then they start to talk with other
farmers we bring in people from
different groups to connect with them as
well and they learn about
you know their um how healthy soil
absorbs carbon more than unhealthy soil
so then they become climate activists
because they're doing that
so there's very much a groundedness that
happens with this as well as this
this connectedness with with different
pers so get that multiple description
which is very much the kind of nora
baits in type of approach that
we're looking at something but there's
so many different descriptions and by
throwing ourselves into the sort of the
complexity of it
and seeing what happened into that kind
of soup and into steeping in that
we get this amazing understanding
because we're completely immersed in it
from so many different ways so
yeah it's never always online um
it's just as like we were saying before
it's kind of the flip side of what
you're saying before
how if you're only just in a project on
the ground
you become myopic it's the same as if
you're only online and so i think
there's this
there's these spectrums and that by
being
part of all them being conscious about
being part of part of all the different
realms i think is really interesting so
i mean
so i'd do the same thing with the course
as well by the time people have finished
that course not only have they got to
know all their local neighbors and and
explored their buyer region they've
connected with the
indigenous leaders of the area they have
designs for their place they've started
developing their gardens
they've started teaching permaculture
and then they graduate
you know it's but it's only through
being engaged in all of that and
um and so the the online part is really
for the conversations it's for the
making sense it's for getting
into the detail of things but it's when
you set up
programs i mean earlier i was quite
surprised to hear you say that the
permaculture teaching
course has 2 000 people signed up to
that means that you must have a
structure where
as you scale as as more people sign up
to it it doesn't mean
like even if if you only
gave um each one of them 15 minutes one
to one conversation
you'd hit a glass ceiling very quickly
on what you're capable of doing in
a normal way 2 000 people is for a
master class so i
each month i run a master class
on a different topic and each time some
uh it's from the group that comes up
with the topic
so that's something that gets woven into
the permaculture course but the
permaculture course itself
has just a few hundred people in it
which
takes all my energy to maintain people
people kind of um buy into a sort of
apple scheme it's just free it's free
okay it's just free
yeah and so so you people can suggest
anything you would run a master class on
and then you
pick the one that that you do next kind
of thing
i don't pick they pick so we kind of put
it out there these and people nominate
and then
um in the chat you know i look to see
which ones seem to be having the highest
one so
the last one was about eco villages the
next one is actually going to be about
community gardens i've done things about
soil i've done things about
how do you actually make money out of
permacultures there was a whole lot of
interest about that at one point so i
just
whatever it is i even did one about how
to do
how to how to do public speaking and how
to
you know share your stories how do how
do you do that
so i've i've done 26 now i think
yeah because you've been in this for so
long and you also
you're both a permaculture and an eco
village ambassador
so there's a lot of like we've taken
different paths but we share
very similar histories in in some ways
and
um and and friends and i'm i'm wondering
right now there seems to be
like i'm observing that a lot of people
feel really strongly called
into community as a as the pandemic
response and there's a lot of the the
hyper educated
and also might as well be honest about
the privileged people
who have a spectrum of choices to say
what am i going to do with my life now
in this
new situation i suddenly say no we need
we need these examples we need these
these lifeboats we need these
these lighthouses we need these and and
it sounds so what i've heard
20 years ago and some some of the elders
have heard 40
50 years ago when when the eco village
movement really kicked off um
how like because we learned lessons
from what we sort of already spoke about
this kind of sinking
into this let's let's just get all our
friends together and buy some land and
live happily ever after on this land
that we steward and care for and
and become self-sufficient and and i
feel like most
eco villagers have eventually learned
that that self-sufficiency is is a bit
of a
missed goal like um you can increase
your self-reliance but you'll never
you can't be self-sufficient in a world
that is based on
being relational beings being in
connection with everything
into being um how can we guide this new
kind of trend towards
let's start communities let's start like
yesterday i was talking to jim rudd from
the jim rod show and he was
um calling how was he calling them you
know
has this game b and then um was it b
communities no it was basic basically he
wants to start
proto b's he calls them um creating
places where people commit to living
game b um and all of that sounds very
much
like we're in another cycle of this
creative process and it just comes as an
impulse and it's
normal but how do we keep it
from people disappearing into these
these little projects and and not doing
the the
um turning what they're doing
into the yogurt culture that turns the
the milk of the region
into into yogurt kind of approach
what's your take on that what i'm
feeling at the moment is that there are
so many
fantastic examples that are out there
that
still are not really visible you know we
have the magnificent eco village network
that connects
so many but if you are looking for what
most people see when they're looking for
housing choices
it's not really visible so one of my one
of my key goals is to
help to make those visible wherever i
can
and so that's part of that eco village
ambassador or starting to take
um you know in i managed to get a story
in
a really mainstream magazine just the
other day just about
um you know our life here and our house
and
our community as just a different way of
talking about it
um but i also think that there is no one
particular way
so for example there's a lot of young
people who've started to move out here
to crystal waters and finding ways to
move here and there they have a sense
that you know they are really well
educated they're looking for something
different
but what i'm hearing them talk about is
actually buying a piece of land
and doing it together but because they
are so
connected differently than what we were
say 20 years ago
because of the communication systems
that we have they will not be
disconnected from the world in that way
i don't think they'll
disappear into that hole on the other
side then there's
you know there's all this whole movement
with um
the retro suburbia so david holmgren's
um latest book uh
yes i i've only seen the cover i didn't
know it was
yeah yeah it's it's huge um it's
actually
available to be downloaded as pay as you
pay as you feel comfortable
online so it might be worth putting a
link to that
um you know on your show notes as well
because
it's a magnificent um manual really it's
called the downshifter
shifters guide to a resilient future so
he's really talking about
look you know we obviously need to
change
but let's do it where we are let's think
differently about the suburbs
you know particularly when we're looking
you know in places like australia
most people live in the suburbs and
actually in the suburbs there's a lot of
spare land
in between the houses you know it's
about pulling down fences sharing things
doing um shared housing and then there's
other so that's kind of the retro
suburbia model and i think
there's a huge potential for that to do
something to
and i'm seeing a shift happening in that
here in australia anyway
then there's other friends of mine who
are working in in urban projects and
doing a lot of
um sort of collaborative design so the
the
newer version of the co-housing model so
there's all new names
for all the things that have been around
for a while but i can kind of see that
you know there's a lot of this
really engaged design process so like a
community design or citizen design
kind of engagement in that and creating
shared spaces but
i don't know what's going to happen with
that now because of covert
you sort of wonder where that design
shift is going to happen because
there was this whole thing about people
going into smaller
units but having more shared lounge room
shared kitchen shared laundry
and that seemed to be the big trend in
urban living
but if people are sort of going oh i
don't know if i want to share so much
now with covert
then whether we might need to think
differently again about it so this
i think we're kind of we're in the soup
at the moment and i'm not sure what
which direction it's going to go well i
i have
and of course it's a tricky one because
the minute you like if you create
i've certainly heard some people talking
about sort of bubble formation in the
sense of
um creating a social network of people
who share adjacent pieces of land that
that you then in case of future
lockdowns
um you know that
you have this group of people that you
still have interactions with
um because you trust that they are also
taking
the right precautions and then you have
a sort of shared level of
of um how to respond to precaution with
regard to the virus
but it's i mean again it's i think
that's for some privileged people that
they can possibly sort themselves out
that way or
other people just do it naturally with
two or three neighbors and
the kind of properties that that join
together in their backyard
back backyard but um yeah
it's it's a tricky one i see it in my
own life right now with
having a three-year-old and um really
having taken the approach that the first
two or three years
it's okay to be in a quite close to mama
and papa um like mainly focused on us
because if you look at child development
that's really what what they're mainly
needing the the the support um of their
direct parents but then comes that
really important socialization phase
where they need to engage with lots of
other kids and see
other parenting models and the whole
takes a village to raise a child
and now finding this bizarre situation
that
that we need to think about how do we
help her socialize without putting her
and ask
at risk and um yeah
it's it's it's a little bit concerning
just at a point where we really need to
um rapidly
cultivate social cohesion and
collaboration at the neighborhood and
community level again
to now have to do this
virtually even if the guy's sitting next
door because you can't go and have a
meeting with more than three people or
five people or 15 people
yeah um it's i haven't
i haven't seen mandy for mandy macklin
from irma
who mentioned her a couple of times for
months
and we're on the same island it's um
yeah we're in the soup um
it is and you know it's it's um
it's i've actually and you know i feel
incredibly
privileged you know we talk about
privilege that to be in this place
here at crystal waters because we
there is a kind of a sense of a bubble
here that there's
we have this sense of safety i suppose
within this community and like you know
my friend my friends my my kids have
just gone off camping with their friends
tonight i don't even know where they are
they're somewhere over that way
camping beside the river somewhere with
the other kids and
you know the other night they were doing
that as well and they just there's this
sense of freedom
in this space because we have such a
level of
trust and also that isolation here
so i think that i think we kind of
are in quite a a different situation
than what a lot of people are
particularly because queensland itself
hasn't really got any cases so i think
we're
we're quite quite isolated and
i don't know how i would manage my
thinking if i was
in a different place if i was saying
victoria or in you know in spain
somewhere
how i might manage that it's hard to
know not being not having
been in the midst of that no it's it's
fascinating i've noticed this
like when when here in spain things
started to get really bad
i i could hear just just the way people
friends were commenting
um and and assessing the situation um
on social media um and you kind of
thought well you
in an area where it hasn't hit yet so
don't talk about something that you have
absolutely no
idea of what it actually feels like and
and then when when we were in the middle
of a kind of
pretty aggressive lockdown of not being
able to to go out and having police
patrol the streets and find people and
be quite
um kind of strong state
imposing on stupid citizens who don't
behave
and but but now
right now here in spain things have
opened up and and they're more worried
for
that there's another wave coming and but
it at the same time people in
argentina are still in lockdown and have
been
since early march and
so it really is very different in
different places and depending on your
level of privilege and
it's it's a tricky one so we're in
lockdown as a community
as opposed to being you know like we
don't go out very much from this place
and we've set up a whole lot of mutual
aid systems to encourage people to
you know we we order from the store and
we have bulk ordering and we it's kind
of
so through that community structure that
we've got we've
set up systems to help to to manage
that and to be aware of it but i have
heard a lot of people
talking about you know um wanting to
start up
uh community land trusts starting to
think about
well a few months ago we were saying
well living out in the in the rural
areas is
we don't want to do that we love the
city we love the city life
that's where we want to be we don't want
to do that kind of eco living we want
eco living in the city
and i'm hearing a lot of i'm turning
around now saying actually
no i think the rural areas is where we
want to go but how do we buy land
we need to buy land together looking at
community land trusts where you can also
have
community um housing where it's a rent
to buy
type of situation so there's a whole lot
of really interesting new models that
are starting to emerge that are kind of
based on the things that we've been
doing for a while but
new and different and interesting and
it's a it's a
exciting time in terms of that
you know that emergence of new models of
of housing
and i'm i'm i'm really sort of
all ears and all eyes trying to see what
is happening and what's emerging and how
i can you know possibly support that
and at the same time looking differently
here within crystal waters that
there's now a time and we've got a group
here that's looking well how can we
create
a new village within the village so
there's a new little section that's
going in as part of the
visitors area where there'll be sort of
a tiny home village a lot of people's
homes
where there was just one dwelling on the
lot now has multiple dwellings or
you know little tiny homes and and
cottages and things so we're actually
getting higher density
which is really great really wonderful
yeah so it's changing
because yeah that's the whole density
issue is like how do we
it's so clear that cities have a
footprint
footprint and an impact beyond what
could
possibly be sustainable in the long term
like the the mega cities of the world
but but at the same time um
in terms of the numbers of us to to all
live
in rural eco village idyllic scenarios
is
um also
hard to imagine that we have enough land
to make that possible and
but then like this this just reminds me
of something that we were talking
about in the very beginning that i
actually wanted to pick up on um
which is this whole thing about
rewinding and protecting land
and how that can backfire yeah like i
find it like
um of course
healing ecosystems is the work of the
21st century like
planetary healing and healing ecosystems
to rebalance the global climate
system and avoid the hemorrhaging of of
biodiversity that is going on
um to to continue is is clearly what we
need to do
but but what i'm concerned is that about
is that
as long as we have these mental models
that
separate nature and culture to the point
that culture is other
then you the minute you speak about re
wilding
it's well who's who's allowed in there
and who's not allowed in there
and and as you were hinting quotes that
even indigenous people are kept
out of their ancestral sites because now
this is a somehow a declared
no-go biodiversity hotspot and
it's just bizarre because why is it a
biodiversity hotspot because it has
co-evolved with one species that
actually did its job really well
a custodian species called homo sapiens
sapiens that is actually worth its
name which is the case with a lot of
indigenous
people and not so much with our western
culture
do you get this kind of rewinding in
australia
as well where people are kind of trying
to create these
only for non-human life forms
reserves or
yeah we have a lot of national parks and
which
that can't happen but we also have
uh things like say just even taking
crystal waters for example we have 640
acres here but at least half of it is
being put aside as just being forested
area but not not as a sort of a no-go
zone
we we go into there and we harvest you
know some timbers or different sorts of
things or it's
you know so there's a it is a re-wilding
but it's not a
exclusion zone um but yeah though
the national parks um are locked up in
in many places but
we're now starting to see a shift in uh
into
managing by indigenous communities so
that is changing
which is fantastic and we just started
working um the
global eco village network of oceania
region has started working with
jambon which is a jambon i mean sorry
it's a
it's a kind of a region up near just
inland from the
the great barrier reef and it's
what they're trying to work on is
actually to create that as a
as an eco nation so instead of an eco
village thinking about it as a nation
because as you know
australia doesn't really exist from the
perspective of indigenous communities it
was actually a whole lot of nations
and those nations corresponded with
bioregions
and so where this bioregion um
that corresponds with the jumbo nation
up in the north of queensland
uh does actually incorporate a lot of
forested area and part of what they're
trying to do
is to take more of it back into a
natural
uh habitat but also a habitat for them
as well so thinking about habitat being
not just for other species but for all
species including us
and and i think we also need to start to
think of our cities
as habitats for all species not just for
humans so
it's it's expanding it both ways i think
that we really need to
shift our thinking about that because
that you know our planning system is
like
people there nature there and farming
there and this is what i really like
about permaculture is it kind of brings
those things
back together again and saying well how
can we bring more people into the
farming landscapes and how can we
bring you know forests and natchez
nature spaces back into farms and
into the urban areas and how can we
actually condense our footprint
of of you know what we need for
for living well uh so that we can create
more space it's available for nature to
thrive
um and you know it's part of that is
rewilding but rewiring
differently i think it's not with that
sense of just locking it away
but it's actually about just that yeah
the ecological systems regeneration
which is absolutely critical because
you know a lot of the a lot of what we
understand about why we're in the
situation we are now is because of the
ecosystems breakdown and then it's not
until we start to restore our ecosystems
that will
start to avert more of these kind of
pandemics and and
and disasters from um you know the same
thing with the with the bushfires
because you know the way that the um
ecosystem has been so destroyed and you
know forest destroyed and
the lands becoming more desertified that
we're actually getting this situation
where you know bushfires
just take off so you know
it's all tied together as you know as
frichoff talks about you know
the multiple crises but it's all you
know it's about
how we perceive it and if we can
make a shift in perception and and what
nora bateson talks about too is
she's sort of saying that um you know
her warm data labs is about bringing
people together in conversations to uns
to make sense of things from different
perspectives
and she said actually the shift in
perception is action
it's not leading to an action that you
do this the perception shift is the
action that needs to take and
and we were i had a was hosting a warmed
outer lab the other day with a group of
people who sort of run
various sorts of amazing programs
throughout australia and they were
saying at all the events that they go to
there's never enough space for
for play or dance or music it's all very
serious and earnest stuff and you come
away feeling completely depleted because
it's just
so head-based whereas we're all
reflecting on when there's some
some kind of something that was more
playful
or enabled you to get sort of more in
your body not
artificially created so it felt awkward
but
just to be relaxed and to kind of take
it on that's where the sense making
start to happen that's when those
connections start to happen that's when
it it landed and so we all started
talking about how we wanted to
integrate a lot more i don't know like
playfulness into our into our
conversations and into our
and my children always tell me all the
time that i'm i'm not funny at all
i'm just i'm just actually quite boring
really i'm always talking about
serious stuff and and i'm always too
earnest and maybe it's time to actually
you know relax a bit
but it's not interesting there's this
integration thing because
it is fun and play and it is also rigor
and
and that doesn't mean it doesn't have to
be fun like i find
that i've always said that the the real
contribution
of the guy education curriculum eco
village design education curriculum this
this this work that
ecovillage educators from all around the
world sort of piece together this
this this mosaic of of a map
that um is
for to me is a map of integration it is
actually
um doing something very similar than the
warm data lab and that
that because that was the last thing i
also wanted to talk about with regard to
permaculture is that
for so many people permaculture for so
long has been this
this kind of more like this is a new way
to to grow food
um system and while it's
always been a much wider kind of how do
we
how do we fit in how do we become um
custodian inhabitants of land and and
become
keystone species in the land that we
inhabit in ways that we draw
um from the land in such a way that we
actually give back more than we draw
um i i i'm completely with you that if
permaculture is that bigger thing
yeah but what i've noticed with with the
eco village design education curriculum
is that
you get all these people come in they
come in through the permaculture route
or they come in through the
non violent communication and
facilitation and the human process the
social side of things
or they come in through let schemes and
and
and local um economy work um
or they they come in from a more
philosophical kind of
no it's all about the cartesian split
deep ecology
work that reconnects or all that and the
the reality is
all of those perspectives are needed and
when you when you
do this course whether it's the kind of
125 hour
face-to-face that that max also taught
at
um crystal waters for for a number of
years uh max linda
um he i think he even did it in
combining it with a perma pvc and and
doing it over three months
must have been a wonderful program um
what it does for people
is that it values these different entry
points in in different ways and then
they suddenly see that
that all of them matter like i i
remember when i first
25 years ago wanted to set up an eco
village and environmental education
center in southern spain
for me it was all about strawbell
buildings compost toilets solar panels
um and and permaculture and the kind of
farming sense at the time like let's
like food self-sufficiency um
it was about of course because it was in
southern spain it was about water and
how to manage water on the land but
i was absolutely oblivious about
decision-making
processes um how to fundraise how to um
engage with local authorities how how to
facilitate conflict in a way that
everybody can learn from it
and and it is
all of this coming together that is to
me
um where we invite ourselves in this
into this both personal and
collective constant learning process
that never stops that
that is actually what is the work of
regeneration it is this this
um how do we keep building our capacity
to respond
to a transforming world
in ways that we express our uniqueness
our essence our our gifts what's written
on the back of our hearts with the sufi
would say um in in ways that they
because it serves the wider hall because
it serves our communities because it
serves the world
it serves us as well it's
that that's the beauty it's like the way
for each and one of us to
unfold its own potential is in in
service to the larger whole that's where
we can really do it
um but
that's why education is so so vital like
what you were saying is that this
these shifts in perspective even if you
just take people
through the like as the ede course or
even the online course um
does it's a kind of fast forward
opening a door here this is non-violent
communications now we're going into the
next room uh this is an
ecological treatment system but it but
it
does something to people because people
suddenly see how it all connects and and
and i mean that's why it's so important
that you do your work with
with your um youtube channel and
and your new podcast because it these
conversations like this one
they just offer different facets um that
people can
use for their own meaning making um
so i'm just yeah absolutely grateful
they're doing the work you're doing
oh thank you and you too i mean it's
it's always a pleasure to to have a
conversation with you because i
like you saying before right at the
start you know with our work
and our lives have sort of been along
similar lines but in completely
different places and
and i've known of your work for a long
time and you you also spent a lot of
time at schumacher college and
and you know that to me has been a a
great big guiding light in my place
in my world and i'm it's interesting
because it was actually i was just
thinking then when you're talking about
you know this the inner world and the
outer world and
um there's something that happens that
for me when
when um i'm following the path that i
know that i'm meant to be or
or in service in the way that i'm meant
to be i feel
as i i don't like i don't really talk
about this very much because it sounds a
bit woo-woo but i feel this kind of like
this energy inside that's kind of
burning as there's a vibration maybe
that's what you call it i can't even
describe it properly and it just feels
warm
and it's warm and it's soothing and it's
energizing and it just fills my body and
i can
feel it you know it's it's like it's
there it's visceral and
and when i'm not going in the right
direction it hurts
and my body aches and my neck gets stiff
and i just get
headaches and and you know i could be
staying up
to two o'clock in the night doing work
when i'm in the zone and i don't feel
tired at all and i can get up the next
morning and i can
i'm just filled with the joy and the
love of this work
and and being nourished by the
conversations and the connections and
the
and just what's happening around and
being in an environment
like this as well and it just fills my
cup not just it's like what i'm jason
twill said the other day it's not about
filling the cup it's like
it's overflowing all the time and the
other thing that really
i know when it's just humming along is
when the hours come to visit
and again i don't really say this to
many people but
yesterday i was after i was talking that
i'm also working with a group in kashmir
and
and the um even the university there
said they want to get permaculture into
their planning department and i was
talking to their refugees and that's
something happening there and kenya and
that
agriculture department all these things
were happening
i was coming home after picking up my
daughter from her dance
one of the things she does and there was
just owl after hour after hour just
coming and i thought
okay you know definitely i remember when
i was just coming across
frichoff capra's work in the first one i
was 20 or something and i was reading
his books and every night
my mind was just a buzz and i'd go for a
walk at night i was
in victoria on this island where my
where my mum and dad
lived and this this owl every night
would just follow me
along and then i'd walk and then i'd
walk back again
and it would just follow and it was this
ever since then every time i know when
things are humming along
this out the owls wherever they are turn
up and if it's not i don't see them for
ages and i know i
started to think hang on a tick i
haven't seen it now for a while
but you know i don't pay a lot of
attention to it until it happens and
then i realize oh
okay now i'm in balance i'm inflow i
know i'm
you know whatever it is like you were
saying you know like what's on them
written on the back of your heart that's
kind of
all in sync and it's working and that's
what drives me i
i feel into my work and that's always
been what i
what's before my work thank you for
describing that because that
i think we don't often speak about
that and it's so important because um
i also like they like when you're
speaking about the hour fascinating
because like
one of the nights you know that last
little push of trying to get the book
out and
and it was whatever for four in the
morning and i
really i i was pretty much finished and
i was up on the roof terrace
and um i just needed some fresh air
and look at the moon for a bit and i
almost i got swooped on
by an hour and it almost touched the top
of my hair
yeah and it was really like
i could hear the wings as it as it took
off again
i could hear the wings next to both of
my ears it was literally here
and and here it's paying attention
to those moments as well is really
important because they are
somehow subtle signs of
something is happening and and and if we
listen to them
like i often say say to people
like this this image that
for most indigenous
people around the world if you walk
through the forest and in the morning
and the dew drops are still hanging on
the leaves and the sunlight
hits the dew drop and you see that
little fairy diamond sparkling
that's not just oh yeah some physical
explanation
refraction of sunlight um i've seen
something there
it's it's the the wider
self is speaking to us through these
moments
and and i i think it's like
also what you were saying like there's
this sense of
entering into the flow and then suddenly
energy like you can just
um get stuff done like
a week's work worth of work suddenly
happens
in a seven hour run where you kind of go
oh wow i certainly got into
something there yes and it just happens
and and it's important to also do the
exact opposite to
when when there is when it's just not
right to push to just say okay
like there's no point in torturing
myself right now i
it's not coming i i need to do nothing
so i head off i head off up to the you
know i go for a hike up into the hills
and see what's happening and
see what birds are up there today and
it's kind of like you've you know
heading out on your paddle board or
just going to those spaces where you can
just
be again and reconnect and re-energize
and
and to just be at peace i mean i just
you know there's all these different new
terms for
for that from what is it grounding and
forest bathing i don't know what they
call it but i
is this sense you know you just it's
that connection with its connection with
place it's connection with the other
species it's just
feeling refreshed and feeling like
feeling like i love going out on
on the lake when i'm down in gibson
lakes i can't go to victoria at the
moment but this my other favorite place
from here is the gibson lakes
and i just i just walk into the lake and
i just the smell of it
the feel of the wind in my hair the of
seeing the the black swans and the the
cormorants swooping by
this this for me that's just this sense
of absolute
bliss and and peace and and even i
remember when i was a kid and because
that's the place we always i
always went from the city to there that
was it that was my life very local
and when i was when i was had to leave
there after the holidays
and go back to the city i would listen
to the cars in the distance and i would
imagine it was the ocean crashing on the
beach and i would
and i would um if i was sort of feeling
like a bit
stuck in the city i closed my eyes and i
could imagine myself just
walking along these little bush ways and
it was
it's those little spaces they stay
within you and i think if you find those
special places that they are those
little
sources of energy and connection and you
know
we we don't have indigenous routes that
go 120 000 years
of into this country here but we can
find
and connect with those special places
and we can really
and i think the more that we start to to
ground and listen and be
and and spend time with local elders as
well and understanding
a little bit about the depth of this
place and and what it means
uh you know it's such a
it it feels different than just
living in a place it's a completely
different way of
being in the landscape i think it's
really important to
in a sort of both and way
to on the one hand not pretend like
are we disconnected westerners we can
just say oh we're all indigenous to
planet earth and then then we
we're equal or we have the ancestral
knowledge that
that um indigenous people hold and
the other end of the spectrum to say we
will never get there because we
never grew up in in this and and we're
so
we've got it all wrong and and now
suddenly it's it's all
turned over to only people who can claim
some form of indigenous
lineage which has also been in so many
places
um submitted to 400 years
of um torture and and and destruction
that
that it's not the same
um knowledge and wisdom any more than it
was 400 years ago
um so so i i think we do need to reclaim
the very fact that indigeneity is that
we are born
of this earth we are born from this
earth we are we belong to the earth the
earth doesn't belong to us
um if we don't accept our own
indigeneity
every one of us um and then
with it except the responsibility that
comes
with feeling i mean i
was it's so beautiful i remember
at one point working with john croft on
something and john
was um sharing this beautiful aboriginal
wisdom or practice of also a kind of
grounding
of lying down on the earth and really
sensing gravity
and and how in in the storytelling the
way he
shared it with me it originally is very
often
very early on teach their children that
it's
gravity that
is the constant proof
of being loved and being cared for and
being
held that we are all being held
by gravity by mama by planet earth and
lying on your back looking up into the
stars we all get that moment of
and and i i was just sharing this
story with my my little daughter um a
few weeks ago
and we were lying on our backs and we
were um on the beach and i was just
saying look in australia the the people
who
lived there for a very long time um they
sense this being stuck like
by gravity onto the earth as as as a big
hug
from the earth and you can every time
you need it you can just lie down and
you can
you can get a hug from planet earth and
it's so beautiful because yesterday
two weeks later yeah um lucia just
looked at me and said yeah gravity it's
a hug from planet earth
and it's so beautiful and you know i
think the thing is that
when we when we talk with young people
about these things and when we engage
them in this that
they grow up within this space there is
a deep sense of
like a groundedness and a peacefulness
within them i think because
you know when we when we're completely
urbanized
we don't seem to have that unless we
have that conversation unless we have
those experiences
we can just feel completely separated
and it's such an important thing to to
do this
to do this work and to have those
conversations and to
to engage um young people in that i
was so excited last night i was on a
conversation with them
with the the gen ambassadors from the
oceana region
and one of them was an education uh
officer from bhutan and he was just
talking about how
they're developing up the k-12 uh
permaculture and eco-village principles
embedding within their whole
way of life and talking about you know
very place based
education and i was just thinking if if
regeneration and deep place
thinking is embodied within the school
and things emerge from that as opposed
to
the kind of values that we have at the
moment i mean i know a lot of this can't
be taught at schools it's about what
happens in those conversations in the in
between times but i still think if we
can start to flip
where are education systems coming from
and where those conversations that we're
having with young people and
and to raise the bar you know i think a
lot of the conversations that i've had
with young people are
not at that deep level whereas the the
depth of understanding like i
i'm always amazed you know when you have
those conversations with young people
how
deeply they take it in and how much
it stays with them and like you said it
comes out a couple of weeks later and
you can see that it's been rolling
around
in there and it's it's really stuck
and uh i think i think those
conversations
are just absolutely just priceless
and we need to be having them with each
other as well as our young people
well one thing that as you were
describing your
your practice a little i was also
thinking of um
you know pat mccabe um native american
elder
um she has this beautiful little video
out where she speaks about the power of
um of prayer and
um you can of course prayer can quickly
bring up this sort of
religious connotations and some people
get the whole kind of
uh hackles raised about spirituality
which
i don't want to judge but but if you
really take it out of all the
the baggage um as a as a declaration
and a invocation
of intentionality of saying
like ultimately it's it's it's repeating
your mission
statement and your core value statement
um
to yourself um
and to just the experiment of like i
guess you mentioned yeah that's that's
when i thought of it when you mentioned
my sub paddling out on the bay of parma
i do a lot of um chanting um
mantras when i'm out on the paddle board
and
the blue medicine buddha mantra
basically has this
this repetition phase in it where um it
goes back and say back and say back and
say maha beckons
and and i i use it as a as a sort of um
to send mine the healing and
and for me understanding that that
health is primary and wholeness is
primary and
so you never ask for health as something
that is absent
but you but but to ask for it as
something that is always
present but is sometimes blocked because
of misperceptions or
non-flow um
so that the the relief of blockages of
health as this
scale linking emerging property if you
want to put it into a complexity
language
when when i say this back and see back
and say back and see
i i visualize my own healing
my family in my community and then
depending sometimes
this island and the world or sometimes
also
the world and beyond this world because
i think
while it's wonderful to be gaia centric
um it's it's only part of the story
there's there's more beyond
um even even this planet and
it's beautiful yeah and i've i noticed
that
just that practice of spending time with
my breath like because mantras
just synchronize the breath and so they
put you into a different
state um it is like a prayer when i saw
pat mccabe's
uh video i suddenly thought yeah that's
my prayer that's me
um every day repeating i'm here in
service
for the healing of the earth and her
people and reminding myself that
in order to do that well i need to start
also with healing myself and i need to
start with healing my family and i need
to
heal all the the patterns that i carry
that no longer serve and constantly tug
on my mask to say
how can i change to be more fully of
service and and
able to do this and and i i believe that
it's
it's really powerful when you just keep
repeating
your your core intention and
well because you that's the other thing
you were saying earlier that these
things
and even this conversation i keep saying
this to people it's like to understand
that we are sabotaging ourselves when we
make in our movement
this this distinction between theory and
practice
um between all his great ideas wonderful
frameworks yes but
he's more of a theoretician and i'm a
practitioner or the other way around
both and um the the power
of organizing ideas and and shifting
meaning and storytelling that helps
people to re-relate
in new ways with each other with their
place with the planet with
their role in life with that with their
agency of being
like unable to not change the world
we we all are changing the world and
just to remind people of that little
thing
sounds like theory but if it lands in
the person in the right moment
it changes the trajectory of that person
forever
and who could say that that's that's not
practical
and and so um and i'm totally practical
i mean how
would your wonderful outreach work um
like i get
the odd email what one or two a day or
at least 10 15
um a week of people
who somehow find what i'm putting out
there
um meaningful and then telling stories
that are so
touching that that every time i i feel
like i
i want to stop doing all the social
media stuff and
and finally pay more attention to the
things that i've been putting off
for a while um in in my immediate
chain living situation change like to
get more into the situation
you're in to have a wonderful um
ecologically built home in an eco
village community and
and a garden like the one that you can
do your videos and outside the door
um that's that's really where i feel
pulled that i need to
kind of pay attention to that base
for me for a while um but it's i find it
really encouraging to see how how many
people actually do get
something out of conversations such as
this do you also get a lot of
um absolutely you know i think it's that
often they might feel alone where they
are
and that connecting in with these this
global conversation and feeling a sense
of resonance with it
um just makes them feel like they've had
a sense of coming home
that you know there's other people who
think like them and you know like from
just from that simple kind of
perspective those i get those sort of
comments all the time
um another one is a sense of permission
you know it's not like we're saying okay
you can go out and do that but
there is this sense of opening oh yeah
it's actually okay to think like that to
act like that to do that or
um to go ahead and yeah the stories i
get from all over but
you know the story that i'm also getting
lots of um
requests at the moment particularly from
uh different groups
in in refugee camps because that's kind
of the rippling
that's going out and saying i'm hearing
the amazing work that this group is
doing and they've told me about
how what that's happening and that's
rippling out
and so i get this sense that
once it goes out there's this life that
it has and it keeps going and so even in
one little you know one little
drop of action here you never actually
really know
the impact that it has and um it comes
back maybe 20 years later i've had
people coming up to me and saying
i came into a workshop that you did um
you know at a library it's like 20 years
ago or something and you said this
and and then i went off and i did this
and this and this and this and this and
i'm
you know what do you what what it makes
me think is that
everything that i say and every idea
that i share
and and how i share it is
important because it's it
all of those things have impact
it's not just the words it's not just
you know it's all of that and i so i'm
always really conscious about the types
of stories that i'm sharing the type of
language that i'm
using and the type of way that i'm
offering and inviting people to
participate
in in that and and providing
opportunities for not just activating an
idea but
finding an avenue to then take the next
step
maybe gently to start with you know i've
just finished this series
on plastic free july so we're at the end
today is the very end of plastic free
july so every day through
through july i would just head outside
into my garden or into my
kitchen or somewhere around the house
and start talking about different ways
to
think about you know cooking and
gardening and cleaning and it was like
such micro little tips but it became
you know the thing is when you find a
little point to enter into it opens up a
whole world
and that's the thing it's like what is
that point of accessibility
that i can talk to you it's not
threatening it's not overwhelming it's
just i'm talking to you person to person
about
something you go oh yeah i could do that
but then realizing that by doing that
it's starting to shift the way you see
it's done to shift your perception start
to shift the way you act the way you
connect
the way that you purchase the way you
speak up that you know once you start to
open
up the way that you see things it's
really difficult to close back down
again
and it doesn't have to be a major shift
that happens and
often it's those little things that can
spark
and also that it's it's that
accessibility i think
for me that i've come down to a lot of
the a lot of the work that i've end up
doing with communities in
uh in schools and with children and with
teenagers and
and even with you know in senior
citizens groups of
of you know valuing every person's
contribution
house however big or small it is
that you know say if i'm going to talk i
can get
invited to talk at local libraries for
example and i go in and i
and i look around and i might be
surrounded by a city of people and the
average age
would be maybe 70. and i think oh this
is really interesting and then i start
then afterwards they say oh my son he's
the
head of the architecture thing of the
university of such and such i'm going to
tell him about that and then
it says you know my granddaughter is
that and they and the communication
starts to ripple out and i'm
totally never going to judge oh this is
not going to go very far because you
know
everyone's perspective and everyone is
there because they
absolutely are drawn to being in that
point and that
um you know i don't know something about
i have this i have this struggle quite
often thinking oh it's not
that's not enough i'm not doing enough
by doing that small thing but then i've
got to remind myself about how
you know that how everything's connected
and if it's a gentle
and a beautiful way of offering and it's
taken up and gently and beautifully
um passed forward because a lot of the
things that i've struggled with right
from when i first started becoming an
activist when i was in my teenage was
you know the violence in the world and
the
and the and the conflict and it really
you know whenever i come to that space i
feel incredibly
i know it upsets me really deeply and so
the the way in which i
would like to be in the world is not
about confronting things and doing this
sort of face off
about you should be doing that or that's
wrong or you know stop that it
it is about an invitation it's about an
opening it's about
coming into the joy of being in this
sort of regeneration in a really
beautiful
way and um and that's just that's just
how
how i've found my place in which i can
continue to be nourished
and that i can invite people on the
journey um with me as well
i know it speaks to what i always thank
my friend
um may east for for this reframing of
activism as
um asking the question what do i
activate with the power of my
attention and intention and and
so much more transformative to activate
the
the transformational regenerative story
rather than to
to um fight
uh the destruction and i mean gianna
macy's definitely
clearly named the three areas like
holding actions
seeing within your eyes and and building
new systems they're all important but
but i think we need to find our our
resonance
with who we are called to be and and i'm
also
definitely more activating the the
positive rather than fighting
the the negative but how do you deal
with and
this we should probably come to a close
but as you were saying that
now more refugee camps reach out to you
i
i struggle sometimes with this um
writing personal
individual not cut and paste emails
to umpteen people each week who
are saying i've been reading your stuff
we'd love to talk to you on
on zoom um how about next week on
tuesday or
here 20 pages can you read my project
proposal we're trying to start an eco
village in
i don't know where um would love your
ideas or we're building this
massive international network of
education
[Music]
uh transformation can we
have an hour of your time and i each one
of those projects when you zoom in
into them not everyone sometimes you
think okay they're at the beginning of
an excitement but they're not quite
there yet um but most of them are
wonderful projects where i because of
what you were just saying because
one hour conversation can make a huge
difference
i feel it's really hard for me to say no
um but then i also realized that like
i've had
points where i spent 30 hours a week
on calls like that and then i thought
like what am i doing i'm burning myself
out and
this is not a candle burning on two ends
this is throwing the camel into the fire
um and and so how do you manage
because it's i don't know i might be
throwing my candle into the fire too
oh gosh i don't know um i think i feel
it's quite similar to you that there's a
there's
always something interesting to talk
about another amazing project
another amazing yeah network or
come and participate in this we'd really
love you to be on the board of this and
and you know or be on this panel or that
and and
and i say yes to everything because
everything sounds absolutely amazing
and um so far i've been able to kind of
manage it
okay and
but i do also feel that that um that
struggle you know i live in this
beautiful place
and i you know i'm homeschooling my kids
and sometimes i feel like i'm quite not
present enough for them
thankfully they're a little bit older
than your like my
i've got a 14 and a 12 year old who
quite self-directed um my seven-year-old
just has decided to go to the local
school so i kind of a little got a bit
of leeway there
but i do spend a lot of time late into
the night
and i do try and i i always answer
everyone
individually um i don't hand that off
although i
am like i said i've just employed a an
assistant now who will start to help
to answer some inquiries um at least to
get
initial conversation happening so that
then um
i can you know
it's it's challenging isn't it i you
know it's one of the one of the things
that i struggle with all the time like
feeling well this isn't my
work in the world and i feel really
drawn to to respond because it's rude
not to
and you know i feel like i have
something that i could contribute and
that's the thing that i need to begin to
forgive myself a little bit more for
because i
i feel like i because then it becomes a
sort of
like as i watch my own story about it
if it becomes a story of i don't want to
be seen as the guy who's now
so sought after that that he doesn't
have time to talk to
um a small project in poland
of five people wanting to do something
really wonderful
it's like it's not a judgment like i i
that if it's a wonderful project i want
to talk to them but sometimes
it's literally not possible particularly
when people come and come with a sort of
um we'd really like you to do this by
next
tuesday and it's like my iris sometimes
is full for three weeks
um but yeah we can only do our best and
and but i see you running into the same
kind of
potential overload that that i've had in
you know what i'm trying to do
with the permaculture educators program
you know my
what i'm really working on is sort of
mentoring people to also be working
in this world and finding uh you know
finding a
a team not not necessarily a team that
we're all part of employ the same but
there's this
this group of collaborators that we can
share
share this and say oh i know this person
here could really help you with that
thanks so much for getting in touch with
me but i really think that this person
will be able to help you even more
and just distributing
those inquiries is what i've sort of
started to be to do a little bit more as
well
[Music]
because it's only so much as much as
everything's amazing
and it's wonderful to know what's going
on and be part of these conversations
and
um and so i always really try and make
sure i have a balance between being
really practical very local community
very global and of you know from
refugee camps to you know eco village
projects there's like these
all different aspects and that kind of
nourishes me so there's that diversity
but it also helps me to keep
in touch with what's going from an
academic level to a community level to a
you know to a social justice perspective
to a
indigenous perspective and um you know
it's just i guess that's where i
it's wonderful because i mean you said
said it before like we
we've known of each other for for 15 20
years
before we actually met just a little
over a year ago here
on majorca but when we walked um i mean
that's even recorded you recorded it
it's it's on youtube somewhere that
that walk in sunderland it really felt
like um
like i don't know actually said it to
you but i said to alice is like
maybe there's something my parents
didn't tell me my father went to
australia for a short while
i know isn't that crazy it's like like
you're my brother
you know so it's been yeah
absolutely to talk to you and um i hope
the
world spins in such wonderful ways that
um one like that alice and i can take
lucia down under for a long journey
i would love to go to new zealand
australia again at some point i'm not
gonna fly there
in a rush if we go we're gonna go for
like
months um but i hope that that's
possible
even if we're old and gray by the way oh
i'd just be wonderful
oh well well i hope so and you know
you're always welcome to come and stay
with us and and it would be so wonderful
to share you know many of the projects
and amazing things that are happening
around here and
yeah that'd be so great and i always
dream of one day coming back to your
part of the world too as well so
i'm sure either way we'll find a way if
if
if things let us some you know my year
this year was meant to be traveling to
many different places as much as that
was a
you know that that conflict between
being
fully engaged in projects and not flying
and flying lots that it was a conflict
for me
so i was if that decision was made this
year so to not go anywhere
it's fascinating isn't it i'd be careful
what you asked for i kept complaining
for the last two years that it's just
incongruent i cannot accept all these
international engagements i must stay
with my family and my island
and be more local and and there must be
a way to avoid flying all together
and now and i i i see you yeah
there has to be you know it was a
struggle to start with but now
it's now i feel really great with it and
it feels beautiful
and it's and and still finding ways to
connect so that's great
yeah and have a wonderful yeah you too
and speak to you soon
thank you okay thanks so much bye